{"tossups": [{"question": "In 1979, Carol Petillo revealed that this man accepted 500,000 dollars from President Quezon one week before his forces began a three month defense of Luzon, followed by the Bataan death march and his retreat to Australia. For ten points, name this American general who led the island hopping campaign in the Pacific theater of World War II after declaring \u201cI shall return\u201d to the Philippines.", "answer": "Douglas<b> MacArthur</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Malcolm Gladwell\u2019s<em> The Tipping Point</em> discusses how this city\u2019s rate of violent crimes was decreased by stricter rules on minor crimes, as predicted by \u201cbroken window\u201d theory. In 1964, Winston Moseley shot a woman from this city who was unable to get help despite several onlookers. For ten points, name this city where the bystander effect led to Kitty Genovese\u2019s death in its borough of Queens.", "answer": "<b> New York</b> City or<b> NYC</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Warning: two answers required. These two countries planned, but never took, a joint voyage to map a boundary defined as 370 leagues west of Cape Verde. These two countries debated ownership of the Indonesian Molucca Islands until the 1529 Treaty of Zaragoza, 35 years after they divided New World territory in the Treaty of Tordesillas [torr-de-SEE-ess]. For ten points, name these two countries on the Iberian peninsula in southwestern Europe.", "answer": "<b> Spain and Portugal</b> (accept in either order; do not prompt on partial answer; accept Castille for Spain)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This monarch employed Chancellor John Morton and defeated a rebellion at the Battle of Stoke; that rebellion was led by pretender Lambert Simnel. This monarch, who established the Star Chamber, defeated a Yorkist king with the help of the Stanley brothers at one battle.This man defeated the forces of Richard III at the Battle of Bosworth Field, ending the Wars of the Roses. For ten points, name this first Tudor monarch and father of Henry VIII.", "answer": "<b> Henry VII</b> (prompt on Henry Tudor before \u201cTudor\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Rafael Bombelli is regarded as the \u201cinventor\u201d of these numbers, since he developed the rules for their arithmetic operations. It is useful to color-code graphs of functions that contain these numbers, since those graphs have four dimensions. Euler\u2019s formula equates \u201ce to the i theta\u201d to a number of this type. For ten points, give this type of number that has both real and imaginary components.", "answer": "<b> complex</b> numbers", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "This man described Germans as \u201cswarthy,\u201d even though he had published the first German-language newspaper in America. He served as the first ambassador to Sweden without travelling there, and he advocated for the colonies to join the Albany Plan by creating a cartoon of a snake divided into pieces titled \u201cJoin or Die\u201d. For ten points, name this American Founding Father who wrote and printed<em> Poor</em> <em>Richard\u2019s Almanac</em>.", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Franklin</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This artist captured images of El Capitan and a round granite formation in Yosemite National Park. For ten points, name this photographer of<em> Moon and Half Dome</em>.", "answer": "Ansel Easton<b> Adams</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This thinker explained a cultural absence of rape and jealousy, as well as overall lower levels of stress, by noting a casual social view regarding sexuality. Derek Freeman controversially criticized this thinker\u2019s study of adolescent females on the Pacific island of Ta\u2019u, which she visited while studying under Franz Boas. For ten points, name this American anthropologist, the author of<em> Coming of Age in Samoa</em>.", "answer": "Margaret<b> Mead</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {"question": "Ahmad Shah Durrani established his capital in this present-day country, from which Babur conquered the Lodi Dynasty. The 1st century Kushan Empire ruled from what is now this country\u2019s city of Bagram. Two massive statues of the Buddha in this country\u2019s Bamiyan Valley were dynamited in 2001. The Khyber Pass connects this country to its eastern neighbor, Pakistan. For ten points, name this country once ruled by the Taliban.", "answer": "Islamic Republic of<b> Afghanistan</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man argued that the Founding Fathers believed that blacks had \u201cno rights which the white man was bound to respect.\u201d He heard John Quincy Adams\u2019 defense in the<em> Amistad</em> case and, in 1857, wrote a majority opinion ruling the Missouri Compromise unconstitutional, saying that African-Americans could not be U.S. citizens. For ten points, name this Chief Justice of the Supreme Court who presided during the<em> Dred Scott</em> decision.", "answer": "Roger Brooke<b> Taney</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Henry III of Castile sent Ruy Gonzalez de Clavijo [clah-VEE-ho] as an emissary to this ruler, who destroyed the Golden Horde\u2019s capital at Sarai. His remains were reburied before the Battle of Stalingrad over fears of starting a curse. This ruler caused the Ottoman Interregnum by capturing Sultan Bayezid I [BYE-uh-zid] at the Battle of Ankara. For ten points, name this Mongol ruler who ruled from Samarkand.", "answer": "<b> Tamerlane</b> or<b> Timur</b> the Lane or<b> Timur</b>-Lenk", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man built a fort on Aethelney Hill while hiding out in the Somerset marshes. Bishop Asser relates how this man was once scolded by an old woman for letting a bunch of cakes burn, and he baptized one rival as his godson; he defeated that rival at the battle of Eddington. This victor of the Battle of Ashdown fortified his country with a system of burhs. For ten points, name this ruler, the enemy of Guthrum of Mercia and king of Wessex, who was known as \u201cthe Great.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Alfred</b> the Great", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Flight of the Wild Geese refers to one group of these people who left Ireland. Machiavelli praised one type of them, although he considers them as useless as auxiliaries. Leaders of these in Italy were called condottieri [con-doh-tee-AIR-ee], and the battle of Marignano saw the ascendancy of the Landsknecht over the most famous of these types of soldiers, who were recruited from their cantons and carried pikes. Swiss pikemen were, for ten points, what hired soldiers?", "answer": "<b> mercenary</b> (prompt on hired soldiers and other descriptions before mentioned at the end)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "With Eleazer Ripley and Jacob Brown, this man led forces and was wounded in an attack at Niagara Falls. Martin van Buren sent this man to put down the Aroostook War. This man ordered the executions of 30 deserters who joined the St. Patrick\u2019s Battalion while leading forces that besieged Veracruz. The Civil War plan to blockade the South was devised by, for ten points, what Mexican-American War general, nicknamed \u201cOld Fuss and Feathers?\u201d", "answer": "Winfield<b> Scott</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Hochwald was one of this entity\u2019s over one hundred ouvrages. This entity also included designated flood zones, but it was not extended to the (+) English Channel. It was named after the minister of War who proposed it, and it failed to protect the (*) </b> Ardennes forest. For ten points, name this defensive line built by the French to protect against German invasion, which failed when the Nazis avoided it by invading through Belgium instead.", "answer": "<b> Maginot</b> Line", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A poet during this dynasty wrote \u201cIn these perilous times - I long to serve my sovereign\u201din the work \u201cOn the River,\u201d written during a rebellion led by a Sogdian general. During</b> <b>this dynasty, the poet of an (+)</b> <b>Ezra Pound-translated work, \u201cA River Merchant\u2019s Wife -</b> <b>A Letter\u201d was exiled in the (*)</b> An Lushan Rebellion. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty whose poets included Du Fu and Li Po.", "answer": "<b> Tang</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "He supported</b> <b>high (*)</b> tariffs and sales of public land for federal revenue, as well as a national bank and internal tariffs and sales of public land for federal revenue, as well as a national bank and internal improvements in his American System. For ten points, name this \u201cGreat Compromiser\u201d from Kentucky.", "answer": "Henry<b> Clay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In this country\u2019s September Revolution, Hipolito Yrigoyen was ousted by forces loyal to Felix Uriburu. It was ruled by a military junta called the National Reorganization process</b> <b>started under Jorge (+)</b> <b>Videla. In the 1970\u2019s, the PEN held \u201cdisappeared peoples\u201d in</b> <b>concentration camps and citizens were thrown to their deaths in the (*)</b> ocean in this country\u2019s Dirty War. For ten points, name this South American country where death squads attacked socialists in Buenos Aires.", "answer": "<b> Argentina</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This event\u2019s capture of Gwailor by forces under Tatya Tose preceded that man\u2019s</b> <b>betrayal at the hands of Man (+)</b> <b>Singh. Henry Havelock and Henry Lawrence died</b> <b>during a siege in this event that also saw the Storming of Secundra Bagh and the</b> <b>siege of (*)</b> Lucknow. It began after a rumor that the new Enfield Rifles were being lubricated with cow and pig fat. For ten points, name this 1857 Indian rebellion against Great Britiain.", "answer": "<b> Sepoy</b> Mutiny (or Rebellion or simliar)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}